NAD+ is an essential cofactor
for hundreds of enzymes
including the purported anti-
aging activities of sirtuins.
In this 10-part video series,
I will go through the alphabet soup of
NAD-boosting supplements on the market:
NR, NMN, NA, NAM, NAD, NADH,
NMNH, NRH, and Tryptophan.
I will then cover the
pros and cons of each
and discuss three ways to naturally boost
NAD levels without supplements.
"Do NAD+ Levels Decline with Age?"
Our understanding of nicotinamide
adenine dinucleotide (NAD+)
arose from humble beginnings as a factor
noted to enhance yeast fermentation
in a 1906 paper unassumingly entitled
“The Alcoholic Ferment of Yeast-Juice.”
Little did they know that
waves of NAD-related discoveries
would go on to yield a
total of four Nobel Prizes.
NAD+ is now known as an essential
molecule for all living organisms,
required for the function
of about 500 enzymes,
including, notably, the extraction
of metabolic energy from food.
The 21st century has produced yet
another scientific renaissance for NAD+
with the realization that it was
critical for the activity of sirtuins,
the “guardians of mammalian healthspan”
I detail in my book, How Not to Age.
NAD+ is one of the most abundant
molecules in our body.
Once considered relatively stable,
it’s now known to be in a constant state
of synthesis, recycling, and breakdown.
The entire pool of NAD+
in some of our tissues
is turned over
several times a day.
To maintain cellular vitality
in the face of this turnover,
an adequate supply
of NAD+ precursors
and sufficiently high enzyme activity
synthesizing NAD+ are critical.
The importance of NAD+ is exemplified
by the devastating consequences
of a deficiency of NAD+ precursors
like niacin (vitamin B3).
The deficiency syndrome,
called pellagra,
is characterized by the 4 D’s:
dermatitis, dementia, diarrhea,
and, eventually, death.
Thankfully, since life as we know
it couldn’t exist without it,
NAD+ and its precursors are
found in everything we eat—
plant, animal, or fungi—
but we need to know
how to get at them.
The niacin in corn, for instance,
is tightly bound up,
but it can be released by pre-
soaking in alkaline lime-water.
Maize was exported
from Latin America
to become a dietary staple
without the requisite knowledge
about traditional processing
techniques, though,
and an epidemic
of pellagra ensued.
An estimated 100,000 Americans
died from pellagra
in the first few decades
of the 20th century
before bread started to be
fortified with niacin in 1938.
The pitch for NAD+ boosting as an
anti-aging strategy goes as follows:
all species,
including humans,
naturally experience a decline
in NAD+ levels over time,
and this decline is, in fact,
one of the major
reasons organisms age.
By restoring youthful levels,
the argument goes,
these age-related disorders can
be delayed or even reversed.
Two leaders in the field,
one from Harvard and the other MIT,
have said, respectively,
that NAD+ boosters may
“hold the promise of increasing
the body’s resilience,
not just to one disease,
but to many,
thereby extending healthy
human lifespan,”
and that sirtuin activation
by NAD+ repletion
“may be the most actionable item
to emerge from aging research.”
Of course, they have
both been involved
in multimillion-dollar dietary
supplement companies.
The first premise, that NAD+
levels decline with age,
has been called into question.
For example,
this 2022 review
“Age-Dependent Decline of NAD+—
Universal Truth or Confounded Consensus?”
concluded that, despite
systemic claims to the contrary,
the evidence supporting
the premise is very limited.
Indeed, the most
comprehensive study to date
found significant changes
in NAD+ levels
in less than half of the tested
tissues in old versus young mice.
The human data are
similarly inconsistent.
NAD+ boosting supplement
shills make claims like
“By middle age,
our NAD+ levels
have plummeted to half
that of our youth,”
but the cited source only shows a
drop (in brain levels) of about 13%
between about
the ages 20 to 60.
A similar study estimated about
an 18% drop from age 25 to 70,
both broadly consistent with a
14% drop in spinal tap fluid samples
taken from those over
age 45 (average age 71),
compared to those under
age 45 (average age 34).
It’s unclear if such modest differences
would have any consequences,
and a more recent study found
no significant differences at all
in brain nor muscle levels between
a young group (average age 21)
and an older group
(average age 69).
A study of skin samples found a greater
than 50% drop in young adults
compared to the skin of newborns,
and a further drop of about 60%
from young adults to middle age.
However, there did not seem to be
a further decline from middle to old age.
There was a small study that found
the NAD+ levels in the liver samples
of six older individuals
(average age 66)
was about 30% lower than that of
six younger individuals (average age 39).
NAD+ levels also may
be lower in macrophage
white blood cells
in older individuals,
but in the blood more generally,
half the studies showed
a decline with age,
and the other half didn’t.
By far the largest study
(enrolling 10 times more people
than the other studies combined)
found a slight drop in NAD+
in the aging bloodstreams
of men but no drop in women.
The bottom line is that,
given the conflicting results from the
remarkably few studies on the subject,
it’s misleading to say NAD+
universally decreases with age.
Regardless, the proof
is in the pudding.
What about the second premise
that boosting levels late in life
can improve health and longevity?
We’ll address that question, next.